<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apologie of George Brisset, Lord of Gratence Written vpon consideration of the inhumane murther of the late French king, and sent to Monsieur Tauraine, a counsellor in the Court of Parliament of Brittaine in France, Lord high Steward of the councell of Nants; where the said noble man, with many others of account, were conuerted from the Church of Rome, and become true Christian catholicks, to the great ioy of all good Christians. Translated out of French into English.</title>
            <author>Brisset, Georges.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 630:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apologie of George Brisset, Lord of Gratence Written vpon consideration of the inhumane murther of the late French king, and sent to Monsieur Tauraine, a counsellor in the Court of Parliament of Brittaine in France, Lord high Steward of the councell of Nants; where the said noble man, with many others of account, were conuerted from the Church of Rome, and become true Christian catholicks, to the great ioy of all good Christians. Translated out of French into English.</title>
                  <author>Brisset, Georges.</author>
                  <author>Tauraine, Monsieur.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [16] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Nicholas Okes] for VVilliam Barley, and Iohn Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Georges Brisset: Lettre apologétique de George Brisset, Sr Desgrustières, sur les raisons qui l'ont meu à se ranger à la religion réformée.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Brissets apologie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APOLOGIE OF GEORGE BRISSET, LORD OF GRATENCE.</p>
            <p>Written vpon conſideration of the inhumane mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the late French king, and ſent to Monſieur <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> a Counſellor in the Court of Parliament of <hi>Brittaine in France, Lord high Steward of the councell</hi> of Nants; where the ſaid Noble man, with many others of account, were conuerted from the Church of Rome, and become true Chriſtian Catholicks, to the great ioy of all good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French into Engliſh.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>VIRESCIT VVLNERE VERITAS</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed for <hi>VVilliam Barley,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baily.</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:2"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſhort diſcourſe includes in it much ſubſtance, and layeth open the principal errors by which the trayterous Papiſts haue ſo long gouerned the common-wealth of France: ſhewing how their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are badly grounded, ill applyed, and worſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued for their purpoſe. Therefore I wiſh euery man would haue ſo much care of his ſoules health, as to imitate this new Conuert in the ſearching of Gods word: and doubtleſſe, then many would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue true comfort, and diſcerne light from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bee no more miſſe-led with that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable rule of Popery, viz. That it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for artificers, and tradeſ-men, and thoſe that bee ignorant people, to ſearch into the Booke of God. By which meanes theſe Papiſts haue faire aduantage to muffle their ſcholers in any error, were it neuer ſo groſſe: where hauing their faith
<pb facs="tcp:7012:3"/>tied to another mans report, they muſt needs ſtand in danger of damnation. And that many more ſhould not be ſeduced into the like opinion, here is (by an inſpiration from God) an Apologie made by a French gentleman, trained vp all his time from his infancie in Poperie, now reduced to the true knowledge of God, reuealed in his holy word, by ſearching out his ſaluation in the diligent reading and meditation thereof.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:3"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGIE OF GEORGE BRISSFT, Lord of Gratience.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered (right noble Sir) how that Rome continually ſtriues to build vp the glory of her king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with the bloud of Princes, and to make by the ſame, a legend ful of ſainted murtherers, I grew more deſirous of my ſouls health then before. And that the changing of my religion, may make in you no ill impreſſion of me, but that you would ſtill hold me in the ſame eſtimation: I haue here ſet downe in writing, the motiues and reaſons which haue induced me ſo to do: intreating you to beleeue that I haue not bin led vnto it, by any humane or worldly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. For I haue ſhut mine eies to many
<pb facs="tcp:7012:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7012:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7012:5"/>faire promiſes and aduantages, which were offered me by the church of Rome: and haue loſt the loue of many perſons, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I will not ceaſſe to honor and loue; but principally your ſelfe, whoſe vertue and diſcretion I haue alwaies highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Which doth not onely giue me hope, that you will the better taſt my allegations, which I haue here briefly ſet downe: but alſo that many thouſands hereby may returne out of the miſts of Popery, into the light of truth: in the which God be theirs &amp; my guide. And as my ſoule therein hath gained content, ſo I wiſh all miſ-led beleeuers in that bewitching religion of popery be ſummoned, &amp; call their intellectual ſenſes together, and examine their conſciences, whether ſaluation conſiſteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſimilitude of viſible things (wherein I haue bene in former times nuſled:) or the contemplatiue cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of inward thoughts (wherunto I am now reduced) be the better. Therfore as an induction to this my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Apologie, I wiſh all true Catholickes to become true alleagiants to their Princes, and not to let the blind Bayard of Babylon, with the vaine glory of his outward ceremonies, bewitch you. And ſo with honeſt truth to the world, &amp; feruent faith in Chriſt Ieſus, I begin.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7012:5"/>
            <p>The time I was (right honourable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, and well beloued friends) one of the number of the moſt zealous to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane religion, I had notwithſtanding this perſwaſion with my ſelfe; that religion is not ſubiect to men, how great and learned ſoeuer they be, but that they themſelues are ſubiect to religion: alſo that religion is the rule of ſaluation giuen of God to men, and to which euery man ought to bee ſubiect; and that it is not lawfull for any one to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt himſelfe, or to change or diminiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing therein. And thereupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of ſome Church-men which I had beſt conceipt of, if this rule was giuen of God, they anſwered me, that it was in the ſacred booke of God, called the Bible; and that there is no other booke beſides which may be named the word of God. Following therfore this counſell, after I had prayed to almighty God to giue me grace to profite therein, I painfully endeuoured my ſelfe to reade that booke; and hauing chearefully read ouer all the Goſpell, I was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aſtoniſhed to finde nothing therein, concerning the moſt part of thoſe things, which had bene taught me. And that it is not in the Bible commanded at all to inuocate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7012:6"/>the Saints, nor to render any ſeruice to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, nor to ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt, nor to pray to God without vnderſtanding what we ſay; and that it ſpeakes nothing of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, nor of Lent, nor of Maſſes, nor of Merits, nor of Monkes, nor of religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, nor of the precedencie of the Church of Rome: nor in briefe of any of all thoſe things, almoſt which were taught me in the time ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance blinded me; which things I then thought had bene expreſly commanded in that Booke of the word of God. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more I found (in the ſame) diuers paſſages which did ſeeme to me to be flat contrary to theſe things. Hereupon repairing my ſelfe to ſome of the ſame Church-men, they anſwered me, and ſaid, that it was not lawfull for me to reade the holy Scripture, nor to ſearch after things which ſurpaſſed my capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, but to be directed by them: alſo that the Catholike Romane Church had ſo ordained, to whom the holy Scriptures belongeth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: that ſhe is <hi>the pillar and ground of truth.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. verſ. 15. <hi>VVho heareth not the Church, let him be vnto thee as a heathen man, or a publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane. Matth.</hi> 18. And that Ieſus ſaid to Saint <hi>Peter, I haue prayed that thy faith may not faile thee.</hi> Whereby it appeareth that the Church
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7012:6"/>of Rome founded vpon Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> cannot erre in the points of faith, as they of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſect affirme.</p>
            <p>Whereupon aduiſedly pondering theſe things in my minde, I ſaid: I beleeue that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt dyed for me, and that the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes contained in the booke of the word of God, doe appertaine vnto me as well as to Clergie-men: wherefore then ſhould I not preſume to ſee theſe things which appertaine vnto me? Contrariwiſe, if I had books of loue, or of tales and fables, they ſhould not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from me; but now theſe men would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue me of the booke which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſay is the booke of Gods word. Adde to this; if it be for none to reade but the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, neuer any man ſhould prepare himſelfe to reade it, ſeeing hee cannot be learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he haue read it. I had thought one had read the Scriptures to become wiſe in piety; behold theſe men would, that one ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come wiſe before he had read it: wherefore then do they alledge paſſages out of the holy Scriptures, ſeeing they will not permit me to ſearch whether their allegations bee true or not? My minde was therefore to ſee thoſe places which they did alledge vnto me for the authority of the Church of Rome.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7012:7"/>Now for the firſt, where the Church is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the pillar and ground of truth, I finde it there, no waye ſpoken of the Romane Church, no more then of the Grecian or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Church: there being alſo no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that the diuine veritie ſhould be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon men, but much more conuenient that men ſhould ground themſelues vpon the word of God. And therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by theſe words only vnderſtood that the church is eſtabliſhed by God in earth, to ſuſtaine and defend the truth againſt infidels, and the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of truth; and that theſe words do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto the Church, her duty whereunto ſhe is bound, and not at all her authority. So the Church of Syria planted by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, was the pillar and ground of truth againſt the Iewes and Pagans; but this did not exempt it from errour. The like may happen to the Church of Rome. As for the ſecond place, which ſaith: <hi>He that hearth not the Church, let him be vnto thee as an heathen man, or a publicane:</hi> by reading the whole place, I finde eaſily that theſe words cannot ſerue to ſhew, that the Church of Rome which they call Catholicke, that is to ſay, vniuerſall, ſhould be iudge of the differences of religion. Firſt, becauſe there is not any mention at all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7012:7"/>in that place of the Church of Rome. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe the doubts of religion are not there ſpoken of, but the quarrels and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betweene two brethren; where alſo it followeth, that he ſpeaketh not of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke or vniuerſall Church: for to end the priuate quarrels betweene two brethren, we muſt not expect the iudgment of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church. Therfore by the Church in this place, he meant the Paſtors or gouernours of ſome particular Church, labouring to appeaſe the differences betwixt particular perſons, and that according to the rule of Gods word. He that will not then reforme and ſubmit himſelfe vnto them, is put into the rancke of Pagans.</p>
            <p>Now to the third text, the conſequence thereof ſeemes very harſh vnto me, <hi>Peter, I haue prayed that thy faith may not faile:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church of Rome cannot erre. For the reading through this whole place of Scripture, doth euidently ſhew, that Ieſus Chriſt doth not ſpeake to the Church, nor of the Church; but that he ſpeaketh to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> preparing him to the temptation into which he forſaw, that hee ſhould ſhortly fall, and renounce his Sauiour. Ieſus Chriſt therfore promiſeth him by thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7012:8"/>words, that his faith ſhould not finally faile in this his temptation, but that God would raiſe it againe from that fall; where if by Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> he had meant the Church of Rome, is it poſſible he ſhould not expound himſelfe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there, nor in any other place? Beſides, if our faith reſt it ſelfe vpon theſe preſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is to ſay, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath bene head of the vniuerſall Church, and that hee hath made the Biſhop of Rome his ſucceſſor, not onely in the Biſhopricke of Rome, but alſo in the charge of head of the Church; and that this charge hath ſucceeded euer ſince Chriſt, without varying in doctrine, and without interruption of ſucceſſion: how is it that the people can bee aſſured thereof, ſeeing that for to know it, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to haue read ouer many hiſtories, both ancient &amp; moderne authors, written in latine, which they vnderſtand not? In all this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I not ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>I muſt alſo confeſſe here, that hauing bene taught that the Church of Rome holds, that the conſecration, and the tranſubſtantiation is not effected in the Maſſe, if the Prieſt haue not intention to conſecrate, I haue bene ſeazed with feare of being an idolater, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, that very often the Prieſt hath his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7012:8"/>intention elſewhere; or beleeueth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the very thing he doth; for he may be a ſcoffer, or a prophane perſon. Some there be, that in ſuch a caſe adore that which the Prieſt lifts vp; worſhip bread, and call it their God, and their Creator. This perplexity is befallen me through the reading of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, where I haue found the inſtitution of the Sacrament litle agreeing with that which the Prieſt doth in the Maſſe. 1. For there I find that all thoſe that were preſent, did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; but here ordinarily the Prieſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eateth. 2. Alſo euery one there receiues both kinds: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the people, commandeth them to proue themſelues, and then to drinke of that cup: but at this day the cup is vtterly taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the people. 3. Ieſus Chriſt did not there lift vp the hoaſt, as doth the Prieſt. 4. the Apoſtles did not adore the hoaſt, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do at this day. 5. In all the whole inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſacrament, there is no mention made of ſacrifice, nor any command to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice Ieſus Chriſt for the liuing and the dead. 6. Chriſt ſpake in a language which thoſe that were preſent vnderſtood. 7. The Goſpell ſaith, that Ieſus Chriſt tooke bread and brake it. The Church of Rome on the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7012:9"/>contrary, ſaith, that the Prieſt doth not breake bread, but the Audience. 8. The Goſpell ſaith, that which Ieſus Chriſt gaue, was his body, (it ſaith alſo that he gaue bread.) The Church of Rome on the contrary, holdeth, that the bread is not the body of Chriſt, but that it ceaſeth to be bread, and is conuerted, and tranſubſtantiated into the body of our Sauiour; which is as much as to corrupt the words of Ieſus Chriſt. 9. I finde alſo in Saint <hi>Matthew.</hi> 26. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. and in Saint <hi>Marke</hi> 14. and in <hi>Luke</hi> 22. that Ieſus did drinke of the fruite of the vine, that is to ſay, wine, with his diſciples; it was therfore wine then when he dranke it. 10. I haue alſo found in the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in ſeuerall places, as in the 1. to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. &amp; ſo forward, that we breake and eate bread; alſo he ſaith in theſe words; This is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, and the bread which we breake is the communion of the body of Chriſt. But the Church of Rome denies all this, and ſaith, that this is not bread at all, and that we do not at all breake bread, but the figure of bread: how is it then that theſe appearances of bread ſhould bee the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Chriſt? 11. Finally, I ſee that the Goſpell, according to Saint
<pb facs="tcp:7012:9"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> the 22. chapter, and the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the eleuenth chapter of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians, verſe</hi> 25. do preſcribe vnto vs, how theſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> ought to be vnderſtood. For when it came to be ſpoken of the cuppe, in ſtead of that which is in Saint <hi>Matthew, This is my bloud,</hi> they tearme it thus: <hi>This Cuppe is the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my bloud.</hi> The bread therefore is the body of our Sauiour in the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, that that which is the cuppe is the new teſtament. Now it is not in ſubſtance, but ſacramentally, as our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt alſo calleth it a commemoration or remembrance. I adde to this, that if the cuppe be the new teſtament, in the bloud of our Sauiour, as ſaith Saint <hi>Luke;</hi> it is not then the bloud of our Lord: for the bloud of our Lord, is not in the bloud of our Lord. Moreouer I confeſſe, that in the depth of my ignorance, it deſpighted me much to heare ſome of the reformed religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vs, in that our Prieſts made God, and after ſold him for a little money in their priuate Maſſes; and I haue heard ſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the Romane Church hold, and maintaine, that the bleſſed body of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt might bee carryed
<pb facs="tcp:7012:10"/>away by a mouſe; which were able to make any mans heart tremble, that loued the honour of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the ſonne of the euerliuing God. Likewiſe to diſperſe the bloud of our Sauiour into ſo many places, and to incloſe his whole en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body into an aume of bread, is not conformable and agreeing to the Goſpell, which attributeth to him a body like vnto ours, to the end he ſhould be our brother. Now thoſe that alledge his body glorified, doe not conſider at all that when hee inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the Sacrament, his body was yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorified; and which is more, the glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath nothing changed his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but hath onely taken away from it all infirmities.</p>
            <p>I haue alſo learned in the Church of Rome, that the ſacrifice of the croſſe, that is to ſay, the death of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, is our ſole meanes of redemption; notwithſtanding the Prieſts ſay, that the Maſſe is the ſame ſacrifice of the Croſſe, and that they ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt really and effectually for our redemption: which to mee ſeemeth very diſagreeable. For the one tels mee, the death of Ieſus Chriſt is the onely price of our redemption;
<pb facs="tcp:7012:10"/>and now they giue vs the ſacrifice of the Maſſe for the ſame effect, which is not the death of Ieſus Chriſt. And it cannot be ſaid, that the Maſſe is the continuation of the ſacrifice of the croſſe; for it ſhould bee then the continuation of the death of Ieſus Chriſt: and ſo Chriſt ſhould dye continually.</p>
            <p>Purgatory alſo is another peece of popery, which hath turned me from the Romiſh Church, ſince I haue found it to be grounded vpon this Maxime, that Ieſus Chriſt by his death and ſufferance hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for the ſinnes commtted before bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but hath not ſatisfied for the ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after baptiſme. For I haue ſaid with my ſelfe, this is the moſt important poynt of all Chriſtian religion: for it declareth vnto vs what it is that Chriſt hath done for vs. It is neceſſary therefore that this poynt aboue all others, ſhould bee expreſly and truly grounded vpon the word of God: yet notwithſtanding, I could neuer finde any thing in the word of God, that could ſhew me one ſillable for it. Then hath not Ieſus Chriſt paid ſufficiently to deliuer vs from Purgatory: and if hee hath paide ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, wherefore doth not God accept of that paine, for ſo much as it is worth?
<pb facs="tcp:7012:11"/>And ſeeing hee doth ſtill intercede for vs in heauen, wherefore do not ſoules come forth from Purgatorie rather at his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in heauen, then through the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of the Pope?</p>
            <p>Alſo the Church of Rome holdeth, that all the faithfull which ſhall bee aliue at the laſt day of iudgement, ſhall not goe at all into Purgatorie. Could not God then as well free vs without wronging his diuine iuſtice? Nothing indeede that is defiled, ſhall enter into Paradice. But Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, and firſt chapter, ſaith, <hi>That the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne.</hi> Likewiſe, according to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Romiſh Church, in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinnes are not cleanſed, but are onely there puniſhed; and torments are no purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make cleane the ſpots and polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſoules and their ſinnes, but inflicting penalties: but Ieſus Chriſt hee doth cleanſe vs from all ſinne, and makes vs cleare without ſpotte or filth. And needes muſt it indeed bee, that it belongeth to God himſelfe to preſcribe the meanes to worke our redemptions, and not for vs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the way at our owne pleaſure. And the meanes for vs to applie Gods grace
<pb facs="tcp:7012:11"/>and mercie, is not to diſplaye his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in tormenting vs in fire. And to the ſame effect the holy Scriptures doe ſhewe vs diuers examples of ſome perſons receiued into paradice, and that haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into peace and glory immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their death, as the Theefe vpon the croſſe. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. verſ. 24. But wee finde not one example of any body which hath bene ſent into Purgatorie. It hath bene alſo no ſmall matter, to finde out the errours of this Purgatorie, when I haue ſeene by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that this fire burned for gaine and auarice. It is not knowne that euer parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Maſſes were ſung, but for ſuch perſons as payed well for them; the poore muſt be contented with the generall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers of the Church, of which the rich likewiſe hath his ſhare; but neuer was it ſeene (at any time) that the begging Friers would goe to the buriall of a poore perſon; and yet notwithſtanding, his ſoule coſt Ieſus Chriſt as deare, and is no leſſe precious in the ſight of God, then the ſoule of an Emperour. The letters of indulgence and diſpenſation that the Pope granteth, are but for perſons of ranke and qualitie to him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7012:12"/>
            <p>This alſo hath greatly moued me, that is, that they teach in the Church of Rome, that a man cannot bee aſſured of his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I ſaid to my ſelfe, ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in ſuch a religion, in the which after I haue laid a foundation of merits and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and alſo bought the ſame pardons of others, in the end of all I know not whether I be the child of God, or a limbe of the Diuell? What kinde of religion is this that teacheth ſuch doubtfulnes? Where on the contrary, by the whole volume of the Scripture, God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs to put our truſt in him, &amp; to fly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him with full aſſurance of faith; and he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that we may haue boldneſſe by acceſſe vnto him in aſſurance of faith through Ieſus Chriſt. Conſider with me alſo (beloued) that the commandements of the Romiſh Church are much more reuerenced then the commandements of God. There they teach, that the Church of Rome giues authoritie to the holy Scripture, that is, as much as the ordinances of men authoriſe the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God. To eate fleſh vpon good fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, they ſay, is a farre more greater ſinne, then to commit murther or adulterie. and yet it was the friday vpon the which our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:7012:12"/>Chriſt did ordinarily eate the Paſchal lambe. To blaſpheme the name of God in this age of the world, is (amongſt them) accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a light matter; but to ſpeake euill of the Pope, eſpecially in Italy or Spaine, is a burning matter, and vnpardonable. At Rome the Iewes hold a religion, which teacheth, that Chriſt is an impoſtor or iuggler; but to ſay that there is no Purgatory at all, is a crime worthy of the Inquiſition. Now euery Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in our country of France can giue abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in crimes and offences committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods lawes; but none can abſolue ſinnes committed againſt the Pope, or his lawes.</p>
            <p>This triple-headed Potentate doth teach many things contrary to the law and the Goſpell. Firſt, God ſaith in the 20. chapter of <hi>Exodus: Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe the likeneſse of any thing which is in heauen, or earth: Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, &amp;c.</hi> But in the Romiſh Church they paint the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, they kneele downe before the images of Saints. Secondly, God ſaith in his law, <hi>Sixe dayes ſhalt thou labour.</hi> The Pope ſaith, Thou ſhalt not worke ſixe daies, but thou ſhalt keepe ſuch holy dayes as he enioyneth thee in the weeke dayes to obſerue. Thirdly,
<pb facs="tcp:7012:13"/>God ſaith by his Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. verſ. 2. <hi>A Biſhopmuſt be the husband of one wife, hauing his children vnder obedience with all reuerence.</hi> But the Church of Rome commandeth, that a Biſhop ſhould haue neither wife nor chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Fourthly, God commandeth by his Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>If any of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not, call you to a feast, whatſoeuer is ſet before you, eate, asking no queſtion for conſcience ſake.</hi> The Church of Rome contrariwiſe ſaith, when you ſhall be inuited to the houſes of heretickes, eate not of all that which ſhall be ſet before you in the Lent time, or vpon fridaies. Fifthly, God ſaith by his Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>It were better in the Church to ſpeake few words with vnderſtanding, then ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in a ſtrange tongue.</hi> The Church of Rome on the contrary, ſay all their Seruice in a language that is not vnderſtood. And ſo in many other points.</p>
            <p>If any one alledge vnto me the multitude of profeſſors, I ſay that Chriſt <hi>Matth</hi> 7.13. would haue vs enter by the narrow gate, and ſaith, that the broade way wherein the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude doe walke, is the way to deſtruction. Therefore if in the reading of the word of God, I meete with any difficulties, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue with my ſelfe neither to be iudge nor
<pb facs="tcp:7012:13"/>interpreter: and that which remaines cleare and plaine, is ſufficient to inſtruct and ſaue me. And truly ſince I conformed my ſelfe, to the true religion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, I haue learned now to beleeue no longer by the faith of another. Nor truly is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſaued by atturney; which makes me earneſtly to exhort all Romiſh profeſſors to doe as I haue done for their owne ſaluations: and to thinke ſeuerally vpon theſe things, that their ſoules may be deliuered out of captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that we may together glorifie God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, being deſirous to bee glorified by him in heauen.</p>
            <p>And now to you, you Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes, as you tearme your ſelues, you that haue nuſled me long in ignorance; now that the true light hath opened mine eies, I will as plainly lay open, and ſet abroad your ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious practiſes, which now to my ſoules ſorrow, I haue bene witneſſe of. Firſt, ye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came in with your miters, robes, and rings, by the doore, as did the poore Apoſtles; but by the window, like robbers, theeues and murtherers, with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and ſuch like. Neuer was your proud power of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly fathers planting, and therefore at the laſt it muſt vp by the rootes; yee muſt in the
<pb facs="tcp:7012:14"/>end be deſtroyed without hands:<note place="margin">Dan. 8.</note> inuiſibly ſhall ye be ſtriken,<note place="margin">2. Maccab. 9.</note> as was the great tyrant <hi>Antiochus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. Heb. 4.</note> with the mighty breath of Gods mouth, which is his inuincible word, ſhall your falſe kingdome be conſumed. This rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon I to be ſufficient to declare you both to God and man, moſt ſpightfull traitours vnto thoſe that will not bee wilfully blinde. And to proue you ſpirituall theeues, is the purpoſe of my writing: for proofe whereof I neede not to ſeeke further then into your owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen acts. How long haue ye kept the eternall teſtament of Chriſt vnder your filthy feete from the peoples reading; which is the liuely foode of their ſoules? yea how many inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Chriſtian creatures haue yee moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murthered to cauſe them to abhorre it? I haue knowne you burne a worſhipfull gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman for hauing but one chapter of S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpell written in her houſe; and another man for hauing S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide many other cruelties by you commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Some haue you burned for not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your pilgrimages; ſome for not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your pardons; ſome for not faſting the friday, for not obſeruing your Lent; ſome for your Purgatory, ſome for your images; ſome for not praying to dead Saints of your owne
<pb facs="tcp:7012:14"/>making; ſome for not creeping to the croſſe; ſome for not going on proceſſion; and ſome for holy-water: and for other vaine tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles of your owne inuenting. Too long were it to recite all your acts of miſchiefe, which yee haue alwaies practiſed to deface Gods word. Neuer were ye yet content that the ſeede of ſaluation ſhould fructifie among the people, but euermore ye haue ſtroue to ſtop the ſweete blaſt thereof, thereby to do the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell your father a pleaſure. Yee are thoſe wilde ſwine, leawd ſhepheards and Foxes, which haue rooted vp the Lords vineyard: therefore how terrible will your ſentences be againſt you at the latter day, where in feare yee ſhall confeſſe openly all your damnable fooliſhneſſe, and that ye haue bene wilfully ignorant of the truth, and haue tired your ſelues in the waies of wickedneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?</p>
            <p>Before your owne faces I will more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe your abhominations, and good workes as you call them. You are, I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witchers of our French Parliaments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yee haue depriued altogether the common people of the Bibles reading; onely you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to three degrees of men, to Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Merchants and Prieſts: all artificers,
<pb facs="tcp:7012:15"/>and men of the commonſort, dearly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as though God were partiall, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his lawes and ſweete promiſes ſhould be knowne to poore men, vnto their ſoules ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the good workes that (you ſay) will iuſtifie you before your God the Pope. Theſe are deeds of ſupererogation, wher with you ſcoure your fiery Purgatory. Theſe are the merits of your ſatisfactions, whereby you get heauen when God is not at home. Oh ſhameleſſe murtherers! If he be called a mankiller that killeth the body, much rather he that killeth ſoule and body. All the world in a manner derideth your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and laugheth to ſcome your vnpru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent practiſes. Chriſtneuer contemned the poore, but bleſſed them aboue all ſorts of people. Not onely opened he his Goſpell to the poore in his owne perſon, but alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted the pooreſt ſort of men to declare it after his departure,<note place="margin">Matth. 28. Marke 16. Luke 24. Iohn 15. Acts 2.</note> enduing them moſt large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his Spirit from aboue. He chofe the weake to confound the ſtrong, and the poore to deface the proud. Neuer ſent he ſuch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Lordly Prelates to ſit in Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, Councels, and Seſſions, to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as beleeue faithfully in Chriſt:
<pb facs="tcp:7012:15"/>therefore it is eaſie to perceiue whoſe ſeruants you be. You euermore call vpon earthly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, as did <hi>Simon Magus</hi> your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour vpon the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> to martyr the Goſpell-preachers. Chriſt neuer willed any to be brought to his faith by compulſion, neither vſed the Apoſtles to enforce any man thereunto: But you like tyrants, more cruell then the Turke, conſtraine people to your falſe faith by diuers kinds of torments. The true faith which commeth by the Goſpell preached, bringeth forth the workes of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.23.</note> which are the fruits of loue and gladnes, peace, patience, gentleneſſe, long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, meekneſſe, chaſtity, temperance, and ſuch like. But your good works, as you terme them, be the going for pardons, the ſeeking of images, the praying to dead Saints, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of holy water, the hearing of Maſſe without vnderſtanding, the wearing of beads, the offering of candles, the idle ſpending of your holidaies, the comming to confeſſion, the creeping to the croſſe, the faſting of Saints eues, the praying for all Chriſtian ſoules, the building of Monaſteries, and chanteries, the charming of Churches and chalices, with a thouſand ſuperſtitions more for your profite and aduantage. Theſe, I ſay, and ſuch like, are
<pb facs="tcp:7012:16"/>your good workes, which beget nothing, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, but haughtineſſe, vaine glory, couetouſneſſe, pride, hatred, malice, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, gluttony, drunkenneſſe, ſloath, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, ſedition, witch craft, fornication, letche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſuch like ſins of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude with this my ſoules prayer: Oh eternall Father, for thy infinite mercies ſake, graciouſly grant that our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and king, <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13. may be ſo inſpired with the true vnderſtanding of thy word, that hee would clearely caſt out of his priuy Counſell houſe, theſe locuſts of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and daily vpholders of Sodome and Gomora, the popes cruell cattell; to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall health of his people: for neuer ſhall he haue of them but deceiptfull counſellers, and hollow hearted gentlemen. Finally (O Lord) take from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their inordinate pompe, and riches, and more godly beſtow it, to the aide and maintenance of the commonwealth. As for an example, it hath in times paſt bene done in England, our neighbour kingdome; where all Monaſteries, Nunneries, Conuents and Friers houſes, were conuerted into ſchooles of Chriſtian learning, hoſpitals for ſicke perſons, and conuenient dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for poore and aged people: reſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:7012:16"/>the reſt of their lands and goods, to the maintenance of their citties and townes. Which godly deede is now commended through all Chriſtendome; and there (O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py country) is Chriſt truly harboured, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, couered, fed, and viſited in his diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed members: all which will be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the latter day. God grant that France, and all other nations may do the like. <hi>Amen:</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
